Pedro E. Harunari

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER · STATISTICAL PHYSICS

Department of Physics and Materials Science, University of Luxembourg, Campus Limpertsberg, 162a avenue de la Faïencerie, L-1511 Luxembourg (G. D. Luxembourg)

Personal Profile

I am a postdoctoral researcher at the University of Luxembourg under the supervision of Prof. Massimiliano Esposito. My Ph.D. in physics was obtained from the University of São Paulo, Brazil, where intensive research and teaching activities were developed. I am an active researcher in statistical physics; my main goal is to understand and tame fluctuations in systems out of thermal equilibrium, alongside their thermodynamic properties. In particular, I investigate systems undergoing phase transitions, heat engines, stochastic thermodynamics, coarse-graining, applications to biophysics and chemistry, and the interplays between them.

Education

University of Luxembourg

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Postdoctoral researcher

Dec 2022 - Current

- Member of the group Complex Systems and Statistical Mechanics
- Supervised by Prof. Massimiliano Esposito

University of São Paulo

São Paulo, Brazil

Doctorate in Physics Mar 2018 - Nov 2022

- Thesis: "The role of time in nonequilibrium: transition-based coarse-graining, phase transitions and heat engines" DOI:10.11606/T.43.2022.tde-14122022-084103
- · Advisor: Prof. Dr. Carlos E. Fiore
- · Allowed to join the program without a Master's degree
- · Approved with the highest grades in every course
- Teaching assistant experience during three semesters, both in graduate and undergraduate levels

University of São Paulo

São Paulo, Brazil

Bachelor in Physics

Feb 2014 - Nov 2017

- 1.5 years of research training activities
- One semester as teaching assistant
- Complementary courses at: IMPA, CBPF and ICTP-SAIFR

List of Publications ____

8 articles published in internationally renowned journals and one preprint.

From Google Scholar: 109 citations, h-index 7.

| • | PE Harunari, A Garilli, and M Polettini, "The beat of a current" | |
|---|--|------|
| | arXiv preprint arXiv:2205.05060, submitted for publication | 2022 |
| • | PE Harunari, A Dutta, M Polettini, and E Roldán, "What to learn from a few visible transitions' statistics?" | |
| | Physical Review X 12, 041026 | 2022 |
| | IN Mamede, PE Harunari, BAN Akasaki, K Proesmans, and CE Fiore, "Obtaining efficient thermal engines from | |
| • | interacting Brownian particles under time-periodic drivings" | |
| | Physical Review E 105 (2), 024106 | 2022 |
| • | CE Fiore, PE Harunari, CEF Noa, and GT Landi, "Current fluctuations in nonequilibrium discontinuous phase transitions" | |
| | Physical Review E 104 (6), 064123 | 2021 |
| • | PE Harunari, S Fernando Filho, CE Fiore, and A Rosas, "Maximal power for heat engines: Role of asymmetric interaction times" | |
| | Physical Review Research 3 (2), 023194 | 2021 |
| • | PE Harunari, CE Fiore, and K Proesmans, "Exact statistics and thermodynamic uncertainty relations for a periodically driven electron pump" | |
| | Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical 53 (37), 374001 | 2020 |
| | CEF Noa, PE Harunari, MJ de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Entropy production as a tool for characterizing | |
| • | nonequilibrium phase transitions" | |
| | Physical Review E 100 (1), 012104 | 2019 |

March 23, 2023

JM Encinas, PE Harunari, MM de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Fundamental ingredients for discontinuous phase

transitions in the inertial majority vote model"

Scientific reports **8** (1), 1-9
PE Harunari, MM de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Partial inertia induces additional phase transition in the majority

vote model"

Physical Review E **96** (4), 042305

Work Experience

(Post)Modern Thermodynamics - School and workshop

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Organizer

· Approximately, 100 participants from abroad and 30 from Luxembourg

- Conference consisting of 10 school lectures, 8 workshop sessions, and one poster session.
- · Shared teaching duties of the lecture "Continuous-time Markov chain: basics, first-passages and thermodynamics" with Ken Sekimoto.
- Co-organizers: Matteo Polettini, Vasco Cavina, William Piñeros.

The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)

Trieste, Italy

Dec 2022

2018

Visiting researcher

May 2022 – Jun 2022

Apr 2021 - Feb 2022

· Visitor at Édgar Roldán's group.

University of Luxembourg

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Visiting researcher

- Visitor at Massimiliano Esposito's Complex Systems and Statistical Mechanics group.
- Supervised by Matteo Polettini.

University of Aalto Helsinki, Finland

Visiting researcher

Dec 2021 – Jan 2022

· Visitor at Jukka Pekola's PICO group.

The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)

Trieste, Italy

Visiting researcher

Jul 2021 - Sep 2021

• Visitor at Édgar Roldán's group.

Statistical Physics seminar series

online

2018 - 2020

Organizer 202

• 21 seminars virtually presented during the COVID lockdown, mostly by professors, for a broad audience of students and researchers across Brazil and other countries. Co-organizer: Carlos E. Fiore.

University of São Paulo São Paulo

Teaching assistant

• Thermodynamics (2020);

- Statistical Mechanics (2018 and 2019);
- Graduate level Statistical Mechanics (2018).

University of São Paulo São Paulo

Undergraduate researcher 2015 - 2017

· Research training program.

• Supervisors: Mário J. de Oliveira (2015-2016), and Carlos E. Fiore (2016-2017).

Skills_____

Programming Python, Mathematica, C.

Miscellaneous Usage of clusters, LTEX, Ubuntu Linux, teaching.

Grants

2021 **FAPESP**, grant for 11 months of internship abroad (BEPE)

2018 **FAPESP**, grant of 4 years for the Doctorate without Masters degree program

2017 **FAPESP**, grant for the Undergraduate research program

2016 CNPq, grant for the Undergraduate research program

March 23, 2023 2

| MECO 47 • Poster: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions" Autumn meeting Brazilian Physical Society • Poster: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions" | 2022 |
|---|--------------------|
| Autumn meeting Brazilian Physical Society | |
| Brazilian Physical Society | |
| | Paulo, Braz |
| | 202 |
| National Statistical Physics Meeting Universidade Federal de São João del-Rei (UFSJ) • Talk: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions" | online 202 |
| Statistical Physics of Complex Systems The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP) • Poster: "Entropy production fluctuation in phase transitions" | Trieste, Italy |
| Bangalore School on Statistical Physics XII International Center for Theoretical Sciences (ICTS) | online 202 |
| Autumn meeting Brazilian Physical Society Italk: "Entropy Production fluctuations in nonequilibrium transitions" | online 202. |
| Stochastic Thermodynamics II Santa Fe Institute | online 202 |
| APS March Meeting American Physical Society Talk: "Quantitative compartison of different time-periodic Thermodynamic Uncerainty Relations" | online 202. |
| Quantum Thermodynamics of Non-equilibrium systems Donostia International Physics Center | online |
| Statistical Physics Seminar Series University of São Paulo Ialk: "Stochastic Thermodynamics: Schnakenberg, FT and TUR" | online 202 |
| Autumn meeting Brazilian Physical Society Talk: "Stochastic pump as a model to study nonequilibrium properties" | online 202 |
| Quantum Thermodynamics for Young Scientists Bad Honn Wilhelm and Else Heraeus-Foundation Poster: "Time assymetric reciprocity relations for an arbitrarily long single-particle stochastic pump and its exact solution" | nef, German |
| | Paulo, Braz |
| series of talks organized by IFT-UNESP, ICTP-SAIFR students Invited talk: "Stochastic Thermodynamics: basics and some modern aspects" | 201 |
| Physics Giants: Einstein Week series of talks organized by USP students Invited talk: "Einstein's contributions to Statistical Mechanics" | Paulo, Braz 201 |

Peer-review contributions

Spanish Llimited working proficiency

Portuguese Native proficiency

(3) Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical, (1) Journal of Physics Communications

March 23, 2023